<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breefe description of the battailes, victories and triumphes, atchiued by the D. of Parma, and the Spanish armye. Sent by the king of Spayne, vnder his conduct to the succour of the rebellious leaguers of France. / Faithfully translated out of French by E.A. according to the French coppie, printed at Paris..</title>
            <title>Discours sur la venue en France, progrès &amp; retraite du duc de Parme</title>
            <author>Farnese, Alexander, Duke of Parma, 1545-1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00960</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123479</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">56572761</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 56572761</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00960)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2143:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breefe description of the battailes, victories and triumphes, atchiued by the D. of Parma, and the Spanish armye. Sent by the king of Spayne, vnder his conduct to the succour of the rebellious leaguers of France. / Faithfully translated out of French by E.A. according to the French coppie, printed at Paris..</title>
                  <title>Discours sur la venue en France, progrès &amp; retraite du duc de Parme</title>
                  <author>Farnese, Alexander, Duke of Parma, 1545-1592.</author>
                  <author>Aggas, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward White, and are to be solde at the little North doore of Saint Paules Church, at the Signe of the Gunne.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1591].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Printers' device on t.p. (McK. 290); headpiece, initial.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Farnese, Alexander, --  Duke of Parma, 1545-1592 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sainte Ligue (1576-1593) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France--History--Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180884:1"/>
            <p>A Breefe Deſcription of the Battailes, Victories and <hi>Triumphes, atchiued by the D. of</hi> Parma, <hi>and the Spanish</hi> Armye.</p>
            <p>SENT BY THE KING <hi>of</hi> Spayne, <hi>vnder his Conduct to</hi> the ſuccour of the rebellious <hi>Leaguers of</hi> Fraunce.</p>
            <p>Faithfully Tranſlated out of French by E. A. <hi>according to the French Coppie, printed</hi> at Paris.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Edward White</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed for <hi>Edward White,</hi> and are to be ſolde at the little North doore of Saint Paules Church, at the Signe of the Gunne.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="description">
            <pb facs="tcp:180884:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180884:2"/>
            <head>A breefe deſcription of the <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictories and Triumphes,</hi> atchiued by the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> and the Spaniſh armye, ſent by the King of Spaine <hi>vnder his conduct, to the ſuccour</hi> of the rebellious Leaguers of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> by nation an Italian, and bound in affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be a Frenchman: yet through fear &amp; ambition grown a Spaniard by faction, as alſo through long practiſe by nature and complection, that is to ſay: as being repleniſhed with vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and preſumption, hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a commaundement from his maiſter the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to paſſe in perſon with ſuch forces as were in the Low Cuntries, to the ſuccours of the Leaguers the Kings rebels, did conſider that albeit his ſaid mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſeemed to be prouoked by the loſſe and reproche of thoſe who comming in March before, neuer returned againe, yet the drift was as much or rather more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, then againſt thoſe that he was ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt: and that his maiſters purpoſe was grounded rather vpon the remoue of his footing out of the Low Cuntries, then vpon any opinion that he could atchiue any thing in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> wherein he was the rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in reſpect of the expreſſe commaundement that withall he receiued, to take with him all ſuch regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Wallons and Italians as were knowne to be any thing truſtye vnto him, together with thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180884:3"/> Lords of the Country that he had any amity or credit withall, to the ende that all of them being thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, and him ſelfe entangled in ſome tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Fraunce: it might bee a fitte occaſion and honeſt pretence with eaſe to bring in an other to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund in his ſtead, which is the matter whereat the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath moſt ſhot for theſe fiue or ſix yéers, wherin he hath found that the ſaid Dukes proceedings in thoſe Cuntries ſhewed plainlye that vnder the title of Gouernour he laboured for himſelfe, as alſo that his ambition tended to lay hold vpon that branch, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer this withered tree ſhould fall: as hauing therev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon fixed a reuenge for the loſſe of his right in <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall.</hi> Neuertheleſſe hauing conceaued all this, he yet déemed that if he ſhould excuſe himſelfe of this voiadge he ſhould haue laide his marchandize too open, beſides that peraduenture it might haue béene a ſufficient ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to the King his maiſter, to declare himſelfe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly againſt him, and by force to enterpriſe that which he ſought to compaſſe by pollicy. Preſuming therefore that he might better eſcape y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one way, then the other: and withall knowing it as yet no time by force to deale againſt his maiſter, as not being ſufficiently ſetled in the Cuntry: beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there remained in the ſaid Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries a number of Spaniards with whom he had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence: he determined for this once to yeeld, and to accept of the commiſſion to enter into <hi>Fraunce.</hi> Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſomewhat to fruſtrate his maſters drifts, and to the end to leaue behinde him no man to ſhut him from his returne: beſides the aforeſaid commiſſion, he purpoſed to take with him alſo two regiments of Spaniardes that were appointed to remaine in the Countrie, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his excuſe vpon the great practiſes, purpoſes and deuiſes that he had in thoſe partes, in reſpect wherof it was expedient at his firſte comming, to woorke ſome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180884:3"/> great effect, which without the ſaid Spaniards he was not able to compaſſe: heere-vpon before any counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund could be returned, he forced them to march, and according to the Spaniſh Prouerbe, conſented to ſome loſſe, for feare of loſing more: and ſo choſe rather to leaue the Cuntry naked, and to giue the States oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to wreſt from him ſome holdes, then to remaine in danger to finde the gate ſhut at his owne returne.</p>
            <p>Hauing therefore reſolued to come into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> he was not content in his own fantaſie to bragge that he was craftier then his maiſter, but thought alſo parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularlye to reape ſome profit of his voiage, and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him ſelfe to be already Earle of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed to renew the olde pretences of the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandy</hi> vnto ſuch townes in <hi>Pickardy</hi> as ſtand vpon the Riuer of <hi>Some,</hi> and on that ſide framed his firſt practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as preſuming to bring them to his own deuotion, yet imagining that if hee coulde not ſo ſoone compaſſe them, he would at the leaſt laye earneſt vpon them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt he were ſtronger: this fruit did he purpoſe to reape of his voiage. The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> likewiſe had alſo an other purpoſe wherby to finde meanes to be rid of the ſaid Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> which was once more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue that languiſhing poiſon that hath lingered within him theſe two yeeres, that it might take effect during his being in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> ſo to haue ſome vpon whome to lay the blame, that he knoweth hath long béene layed vpon him ſelfe: but as the Italians are their craft mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in matter of poiſon, ſo hath the D. found meanes ſo to preuent this drift by good counterpoiſons, that it hath wrought no greater effect then the other.</p>
            <p>Hitherto had the D. of <hi>Parma</hi> béen alwaies an Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, but afterward he played the Spaniard in earneſt. And firſte to begin, when hee was moſt reſolued vpon this iourneye, then ſeemed hee coldeſt and moſt vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180884:4"/> to the end ſo to terrifie the D. of <hi>Mayne,</hi> and to driue him into ſuch neceſſitie as to do him this homage: namely, to come euen home to his gate to begge his helpe, wherto indéed was he forced, yea euen to come to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> where he was receiued with ſuch grauitye or diſdaine, beſides that he came but badlye furniſhed, that in this Court he ſéemed not of ſo much accompt, as euen any his meſſenger comming from him ought to haue doone, as alſo at that inſtant all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spaniards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to haue him in ſuch contempt, that from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth ſo long as they ſtayed in thoſe parts, they abated no whit therof, yea it ſtill rather encreaſed then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſo that they returned him home againe without any reſolution vpon his propoſitions, and vtterlye ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in all matters except of ſpaniſh reuerences and ceremonies which he was forced to learn while he ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Court.</p>
            <p>Afterward the ſaid D. of <hi>Parma</hi> ſuffered himſelfe to be courted and ſollicited with ſundry embaſſages, ſtil waiting that the neceſſity of the Parizians encreaſing: the D. of <hi>Mayne</hi> with his partakers ſhould call vpon his preſence with greater ſubmiſſions, and receiue him with more fauour: vpon theſe lamentable and pittifull ſupplications and proteſtations the D. of <hi>Mayne</hi> alſo for his parte ment to ad the ſame pollicie as he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vſed, in haſtening the firſte ſuccours that he recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by ſending y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord of <hi>Villeroy</hi> to the King, to ſhew ſome deſire to talke of peace, as alſo he counſailed the Parizians to ſend foorth the Cardinall of <hi>Gondy,</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> as their deputies to his Maieſtie, with ſéeming to be deſirous to yéeld, ſo to put hammers in the Spaniards braines, and haſten their comming: which in trueth was the beſt meanes and greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that he could haue vſed. Thus when the D. of <hi>Parma</hi> was reſolued vpon his going, and had alreadye
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180884:4"/> ſet forward his forces, namely the Spaniards whome hee would not leaue behinde: hee began to ſend foorth throughout the world a thundring of his iourney into Fraunce, with the diſcription of his armye, wherein were named more Princes, Dukes, Marquiſes, and Earles then are in all the States of Spaine, and that his power was ſome <hi>18.</hi> or <hi>20000.</hi> footmen, and <hi>3000.</hi> horſe, but ſuch as he painted forth for ſo many <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> or <hi>Caeſars,</hi> able to conquer a whole new worlde if any were diſcouered: he gaue his troopes alſo proud ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, yea euen the Terſes of his Spaniards, ſome hee named <hi>Amutinados,</hi> others <hi>Manſferidos,</hi> and others ſuch lofty names, as might ſuffiſe to make the Mares caſt their foles: neither did he forget alſo to publiſh the ſtate of his furniture, of his great ſtable, of his Pages, ſumpters, and the couers of his foureſcore Moyles and Cofers, the noiſe of whoſe bels he thought ſufficient to make all the townes that helde for the King to yéelde: alſo his great quantity of great locked carriages full of vnknown engins, which at one only diſcharging ſhould carry away a whole armye.</p>
            <p>Being entred into Fraunce, where he found no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance (for the moſt of the nobilitye were gathered to the king) he neuer enquired but how many daies march it was to Rochell, the taking whereof he purpoſed to aſſure himſelfe off by the way, fearing nothing ſo much as leaſt the Viceroy of <hi>Pampelune</hi> ſhould come &amp; méete the King in the plaines of Burdeaux (whether he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined he ſhould flée at the onlye ſound of his comming) and there ouerthrowe him before his arriuall, and ſo take from him the honor of this ouerthrowe which he accompted moſt certaine: Neither had his forerunners failed to inſtruct the Preachers of Paris, who already exalted him as the great <hi>Tamburlayn,</hi> yea the grauers were in hand with pictures of braſſe and marble for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180884:5"/> him as for the deliuerer of Fraunce. Thus with all his Cocodrils teares and Spaniſh ſmokes, he marched on, leauing in all places where he went, the tokens of the moſt barbarous and notable cruelties that were euer practiſed againſt the Moores, giuing out that if the king ſtil remained before Paris, he would not loſe one houre but ſtraight goe and giue him battaile.</p>
            <p>At his entrye into the Realme, the ſaide Lord of <hi>Mayne</hi> ſent to receiue him the Lord of S. <hi>Paule,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time a Page, and afterward one of the houſholde ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Lord of <hi>Beauuaies Nangy,</hi> and now one of the moſt famous Lords of the leaguers armye. But when he came within thrée daies iourneye of Meaux, the ſaide Lord of <hi>Mayne</hi> in perſon with the cheefeſt of his Captaines was to ſée him, but did but ſmally reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the honor of his iourney to Bruſſelles, as being ſo meanely furniſhed, that the Spaniards who thought them all Angels (ſo greatly were they adorned with feathers) did ſo diſdaine them, that they neuer ſuffered any but only the ſaid Lord of <hi>Mayne</hi> to enter into the Chamber, yea ſcarſely into the D. of <hi>Parmas</hi> lodging.</p>
            <p>Being come to Meaux, which was about the ende of Auguſt <hi>1590.</hi> he ſhewed himſelfe aſtonied to heare that the King was ſtill before Paris. There began he to take poſſeſſion of abſolute commaundement ouer the army: And to ſhew that he eſteemed neither the D. of <hi>Mayne</hi> nor any of his leaders for Captaines, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out farther counſell or aduice, he changed all their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and where they were reſolued to marche toward the harte of Fraunce, and to draw toward Paris, he thought it better to take his way along by the Riuer, and hauing viewed the Carde, he appointed his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging at the towne of Chelles, yet was he much amaſed when he knew that the King had preuented him in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing vpon the ſaide lodging, but afterward comming
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180884:5"/> foorth with the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> to viewe the plain, and ſéeing the King comming with a good troupe directlye toward them, they were contented for that time to take no néerer ſight, yea he was more amazed the next day, when he knew that the Kinges whole armye was come within a ſmall League of him, euen into the ſight of eache other: but when from the top of a little hill he deſcried it in battaile araye, a chilling feare began alſo to ſeaze vpon him: for perceiuing in two or thrée ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons <hi>4000.</hi> french horſe, whereof there might be ſome <hi>3000.</hi> gentlemen, and ſome <hi>800.</hi> Reiſters, alſo <hi>10.</hi> or <hi>12000</hi> French footmen, and ſome <hi>4000.</hi> Switzers, and withal among them ſuch a countenance, that he might well thinke that they meant not to trouble him with following them into the plaines of Burdeaux, there to abide the battaile: this poore Prince was ſo daunted and in ſuch a rage, that as it is ſaid he ſwore &amp; blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med God in thrée or foure languages, leaſt he ſhould not vnderſtand him: and complained vnto the ſaid L. of <hi>Mayne</hi> that he had brought him to the ſlaughter, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doo wee read in the fables of any ſo ſodaine meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſis as was there preſently made, for from furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lyons as at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt they were, they were preſently tranſfourmed into Foxes: who thought no longer of aſſailing, but of defending themſelues: and in liewe of appearing any further, each of them fell to making his denne in the earth, which by great good hap was in a Marſh, well ditched of it ſelfe and of a ſtrong ſeate.</p>
            <p>Then had they the pleaſure to beholde this Armye in battaile aray thrée daies on a rowe, which ſeemed as many colde wéekes to temper their heat, that was all waſted vpon the taking of the little Town of Laigny, that ſtood at their backes, wherin he that was the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, reſolued a while to ſtay for them, in full inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to abandon it at their comming, for indéede it was no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180884:6"/> way to be holden, as appeareth by the ſequel, but he ſée them come ſo diſorderly, that at length himſelfe tooke courage and held out longer then reaſon required: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer did madde dogs ſo teare in peces any carrion, as did theſe Spaniards all that they found in the ſaid town, without exception of age or ſexe, either of Churches, which they reſerued for the ſcaffoldes and theaters of their moſt horrible cruelties and infamous abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: which notwithſtanding, yet grew they no whit the more couragious or deſirous of the battel that they had ſo often bruted, for their appetites and luſts therto were glutted with ſéeing it ſo often offered.</p>
            <p>The King perceiuing that there was no meanes to force them to the fight, much leſſe to get them to it vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily or of their own accord, ſhewed them an other point of brauerye, and yet with a militarye diſcretion, which was ſoone confirmed by the effect thereof: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by ſeperating his army ſixe or ſeauen Leagues from him, retaining about his owne perſon ſkarde the third parte, which notwithſtanding they neuer drew toward him, neither durſt they enterpriſe any thing vntill they perceiued him to be further off: but his Maieſtie loath to looſe time, went to beſiedge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Towne of Clermount in Beauais, where he ſtaied aboue <hi>10.</hi> daies, during the which out of this great armye they might haue diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſome troups through fauour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> townes Pontoiſe &amp; Beauais, which they held neer vnto Cleremount, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue raiſed the ſiege, or at the leaſt to haue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted his ſaide Maieſties armye, which as then was weake in horſe, yet ſuffered they the Town to be taken partly by aſſault, and partlye by compoſition, without any their defence or allarme.</p>
            <p>Howbeit while they perceiued his Maieſtie thus oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied, after many their ſecret &amp; great deliberations, and ſundry their preparatiues, as if it had béene to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180884:6"/> thrée or foure townes at once, according as they gaue out: they reſolued to beſeidge the Towne of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beil (the ſame is a ſmall Towne hauing a bridge ouer the riuer of Seyne, of no ſtrong ſcituation, neither ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be fortified by mans induſtrye, as by the ſequell may be well proued) which they that were in it, with commiſſion rather to linger the enemy, then obſtinatly to withſtand him, tooke aſſurance to defend by reaſon of their maner of procéeding, ſo that at the fortnights ende hauing beene beaten with a number of artillerye, brought from Paris, alſo hauing holden out and repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one aſſault, they quailed the enemies for returning any more in fiftéene daies after. In the meane ſpace the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> erected an arſenoll, wherein he kept a number of woorekmen, that laboured night and day, not ſuffering any of them to come foorth or to ſpeake with any body, yea he kept ſo ſure watch that none, no not the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> might know what was in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, inſomuch that men thought it to be ſome deuice to tranſporte Corbeile euen whole, and to ſend it vnto the coaſt of Spaine, but in the end it was found to be certaine boates couered with earth and turffe, wherin to tranſporte Souldiers to a breach made on the other ſide of the riuer. Finally after a moneths delay, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants hauing been too obſtinate, and beaten with <hi>22.</hi> peeces of Ordinance from breake of daye almoſt vnto midnight: being in manner all maymed with the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, the towne was taken by a generall aſſault, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the French made the firſt pointe, yet when the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards entred, they vſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as enemies, and ſlue more of them that had opened them the gates, then of thoſe that had kept them ſo long ſhut: there practiſed they whatſoeuer new inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions and moſt horrible cruelties that their induſtry was able to affoord.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> could not méete with ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180884:7"/> or architects enowe to deſcribe the plant of this ſeidge &amp; Towne of Corbeile, not in ſuch ſtate as it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was, but in ſuch ſort as he deuiſed, as alſo he purpoſed to make &amp; builde a fortres in it, wherby to make it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable, to which end he ſent into all partes of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, hauing ſo far foorth bound this poor ſmall Town, (which among vs was of no fame, but onlye in reſpect of the number of Peach trées that growe among the Vynes thereabout) that now it ſhall be accompted one of the ſtrongeſt holdes of all Fraunce, howbeit onelye with ſuch as ſhall neuer heare what hath ſince enſued.</p>
            <p>After this ſeidge, Parts which by this ſmall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning gathered aſſurance of much better, for the ful fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of their bonfiers, did almoſt make an end of burning that ſmall ſtore of wood that yet remained, wherof now they haue greater want then euer. The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> was inuited thether to ſporte him, the banquets were prouided, his lodging was furniſhed with the beſt of the Kings moueables, the Princeſſes and Ladyes had decked and made themſelues readye, yea there were that euen purpoſed to ſnare him in their loues, wherby afterward to marry with him: But his loues &amp; affections reſting in a fatter and more fruitfull ſoyle, he was no whit moued with all theſe baites. And contrariwiſe being iealous of his prize, he ſtayed there yet thrée wéekes to prouide for the preſeruation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, kéeping his counſails ſecret, wherto euen the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> had but ſildome acceſſe, only giuing out that he purpoſed at one inſtant to ſet vpon <hi>Melune, Prouince Montereau,</hi> and thrée or foure other Townes ſtanding vpon the Riuer of Seyne, ſo to ſet free the vpper ſide of the Riuer, as meaning alſo to doo the like with <hi>Poiſſy. Meulan, Mante, Vernon,</hi> and <hi>Pont del' Arch</hi> that ſtand beneath the ſaid riuer, but all this grewe to nothing: for contrariwiſe finding no great ſafety for him ſelfe ſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180884:7"/> néer to Melune, whoſe gariſon did dayly moleſt him, he determined to retire from Corbeile: which he had no ſooner doone, but he heard that the ſaid garriſon of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lune had recouered it again, and cut in péeces <hi>7.</hi> or <hi>800.</hi> men that he had left there in gariſon, which newes was alſo ſeconded with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> repriſe of Lagny: heervpon the L. of <hi>Mayne</hi> with the Parizians came and coniured him to returne to the recouery of Corbeile, from whence he was not paſt ſix or ſeauen Leagues off: but his firſte price forced him to reſolue not to vndertake it again the ſecond time, as being well aduertiſed, that he that was now in it was thorowly reſolued to his defence: albeit he then proteſted to returne. Neuertheleſſe ſeeing that the L. of <hi>Mayne</hi> had againe ſent the Lord of <hi>Villeroy</hi> to the King to ſéek to renew ſome treaty of peace (yet was not his embaſſage without his knowledge &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) he ment to turne the ſame to his owne vſe, and therevpon made no haſte to returne as he might haue done, but lingered them, in hope that at his returne he would yet enterpriſe ſomewhat, ſometime propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Chaſteau Therry,</hi> ſometime <hi>Compiegne,</hi> which was only to cullour his aboad in thoſe partes, that te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded but to wait whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt mutenous and zealous Leaguers would not finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues gréeued at this parly of peace, &amp; ſo haue recourſe to him to make him their General, &amp; to abandon the D. of <hi>Mayn,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for his part he failed not to procure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be vnder hand therto ſolicited, as giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vnderſtand that he miſliked of this treatye of peace, and denying the graunt of his conſent therto, in hope thereby to trippe the D. of <hi>Mayne,</hi> for he had by experience found that the conduct of an armye or any great enterpriſe could not beare two equall powers, becauſe that growing vpon diuerſity of accidents, they would alſo bréede di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of opinions, whereby each parte being of force
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180884:8"/> ſufficient to maintain his opinion, it was neceſſary for either of them to ſtand in feare of his companion, and ſo conſequently he ſought to aſſure him ſelfe, which could not be without the ouerthrowe of the one or the other. Héereto he imagined that he might attaine by the ouerthrowe of the Duke of <hi>Mayne:</hi> but the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards had in Fraunce borne themſelues ſo inſolentlye and that indifferently, againſt aſwell thoſe that called them as thoſe whome they pretended to ſubdue: that the people abhorred them more then death it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thus ſéeing him ſelfe then fruſtrate of the drifte wherby he pretended to recouer the reputation that he had loſt in this voyage, he iudged that héereafter euery thing would grow woorſe for him, and therefore in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt reſolued to departe: but therein alſo he found one let that hindred his imagined diligence. For the King ſéeing that come to paſſe, which at the beginning (yet with diſcretion and iudgement) he had foretold of the D. of <hi>Parmas</hi> comming: namely, that he ſhould be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to retire before the yéere were at an end, thought it alſo neceſſary not only for his owne reputation, but alſo for the reſtrayning of him from all ſurprizes in his returne, to holde him as ſhort as he might: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore determined euen in diſcretion to be preſent himſelf: and as he is alwaies reſolute in his opinions, ſo hath he two incomparable qualities, namely ſpéede and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in his executions, which commonly are moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured by fortune, and doo alwaies bring forth the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and moſt wonderfull effects.</p>
            <p>Vpon this reſolution, without any noiſe he depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the fourth day of Nouember from Eſcouis in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy, with one troup of horſe and an other of harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buziers on horſeback without any cariages, leauing his mayne battaile with the Lord Marſhall <hi>Biron,</hi> to employ according as they had concluded, and ſo came
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180884:8"/> with all ſpéed to Compiegne, where immediatly vpon his arriuall he inuited al the nobility of Picardy which is great, to come to aſſiſt him to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honour of his houſe, to reconduct the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> out of Fraunce, who had deſerued that fauor at his hands, if not for any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice doone, yet for the ſmall hurt that he had ſuſtayned by him, whereupon within a fewe dayes he had nye a thouſand good horſe, with whom he began to ſéek after the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> who craued none of theſe curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, but could haue béene content to haue ſtopped the belles of his Moyles ſo to paſſe with leſſe noyſe, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loath to aduenture to paſſe the Cuntry of Picardy with his owne troopes alone in the Kings face, who had no footmen, neither halfe ſo many horſemen as he, he vrged the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> to aſſemble all his horſe to accompany him, as not caring greatly what might become of <hi>Mayne,</hi> ſo himſelf were in ſafety, and ſo ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his ſuccour.</p>
            <p>His maieſtie alſo for his part ſent for the Duke of <hi>Neuers</hi> to bring him as many horſe as he might, to the end to furniſh himſelfe the more honourablye: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could ioyne, knowing that the Duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> marched, he was ſtraight at his héeles, and at his firſt comming ſending his men to the warre, the <hi>22.</hi> of the ſaid moneth, he defeated a whole company of Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards without the loſſe of any of his, or ſauing any of the others. The fiue and twentith, himſelfe purpoſed to view them, and hauing ſent before the Lord Baron of <hi>Biron,</hi> Marſhall of the Campe of his army, with ſome troupe of horſe, himſelfe followed at hand with an other: raiſing ſuch an allarme in the enemyes Campe, that he drew them all againſt him ſelfe, and in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces charging them a dozen times, he retired with leſſe then two hundreth horſe without any loſſe, hauing ſo amazed them, that they encamped all night at their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180884:9"/> firſt lodging: At his departure thence, his Maieſtie found himſelfe within one leage of the Duke of <hi>Mains</hi> lodging, wherupon ſuddenly without drawing bit, he purpoſed to finde him at his bed, but that good Prince being therof aduertiſed, preſently getteth on his bootes againe, taketh horſe and at randon caſteth himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Duke of <hi>Parmas</hi> armes, leauing that quarter ful of cariages and ſick perſons.</p>
            <p>Within few daies after the ſaide D. of <hi>Neuers</hi> ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the king with a good troope, as did alſo the L. of <hi>Gyury</hi> maiſter of the Campe of his light horſemen, and the Lord of <hi>Parabelle,</hi> who returned from Melune, where becauſe he could not ſée his highneſſe, he would not let him departe without kiſſing his handes. This renforte being come to his maieſtie, al his men became better courtiers then before, for dayly they were with the Dukes highneſſe at his vpriſing and downelying, and ſtill with new booties, albeit he marched ſo cloſe, that he tooke not the twentith parte of his ordinarye lodging, leauing without pitie or mercy, a tayle of his people that could not make ſo good ſpéed, of whome the peaſants alſo had as little. Thus in this feare, with this ſhame, a bitter repentance for his entrye into Fraunce, and good proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s neuer to return again, the D. of <hi>Parma</hi> with as much of his armye as could ſaue it ſelfe, was driuen away, leauing the good D. of <hi>Mayne</hi> to attend in his returne, whatſoeuer it may pleaſe God.</p>
            <p>In the meane time the King went to S. Quintins to refreſh him ſelfe, where he was magnificallye recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and ſoone after the Towne of Corbie was reſtored into his Maieſties obedience, through the good conduct of the Lord of <hi>Humiers,</hi> and other noble men that fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that enterprize: a town of very great importance, in reſpect of the ſcituation, as ſtanding in the middeſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180884:9"/> betwéene Amiens, Perone and Dourlens, to whome togither with other the townes of Pickardy, this will be a ſcourge, as in ſhort time will appeere.</p>
            <p>This is the true diſcriptions of the battailes, victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and triumphes of the D. of <hi>Parma</hi> throughout his whole voiage, theſe be the crownes and pillers whoſe inſcriptions were ready prouided: he came to plant a Colony of Spaniards in Fraunce, but he did but ſowe it abroad in the fieldes, which haue lyne couered with their dead, out of whoſe aſhes they ſhall not ſpring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as dooth the Phenix, for out of ſuch carrions can proceed nothing but ſerpents and other ſuch venomous beaſtes: and the battaile which this poore Prince tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe a principall pointe of induſtrye imagined to haue eſcaped in great, he loſt by retaile: for it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that of all the great numbers of horſemen and footmen that he brought in, he carried away not paſt <hi>7.</hi> or eight thouſand, and thoſe in ſuch ſtate, as if they had come foorth of ſome ſpittle houſe: he came to reſtore Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris into liberty, to take againe all the Townes that holde for the King in the Prouinces thereabout, and to ſend him beyond the Riuer of Loyre: but he hath left Paris in greater want then before, as hauing all the riuers ſtraighter cloſed vp both aboue and beneath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer they were: ſo farre alſo hath he béene from reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering any one towne, that the King hath wonne one euen before his face: beſides that after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King had him in chaſe, the L. marſhall <hi>Biron</hi> hath recouered what by force and what by compoſition, foure Townes, and aboue twenty fortreſſes and caſtles wherein the enemy kept garriſon: hauing as his maieſties cauſe is moſt iuſt, proſecuted the warre againſt them, eſpeciallye by the executioners of high iuſtice: he came alſo to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chace authority in Fraunce, and to ſtrengthen himſelf with practiſes and fréendſhip, but hath loſt all his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180884:10"/> in this parte: for they haue accuſed him to haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed his maiſter, and the Spaniſh name is grown ſo odious among them, that they are ready to enter leage to goe and leauy warre in Spaine, in reuenge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages and inſolencyes that they haue receiued. This poore Prince who findeth himſelfe ſicklye and of no long life, came with intent heere to ſhut vp the ſteppe of all his labours, by ſome notable act which might haue made his memory famous, and vphelde that vaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation which with ſmall labour and leſſe merite he had already purchaſed: but contrariwiſe he hath héere encurred a reproche and ſhame which will giue ſuch a blemiſh to his reputation as will neuer be wiped out againe. But if in this voiage he hath doon his maiſters buſineſſe but badlye, as hauing ſpent him a million of golde, and loſt him a great number of his beſt men, and returning loaden with nothing but gréefe and ſhame, euen at their hands in whoſe help he came: he hath yet made a wurſe market in the Lowe Cuntries that are vnder his charge, where the Earle of <hi>Naſſawe</hi> and the States during his being in Fraunce, haue taken the townes of Steenbergue in Brabant, and Oudemborg in Flaunders, with twenty other holdes, and <hi>30.</hi> or <hi>40.</hi> péeces of Ordinance in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Moreouer beſides all theſe miſchiefes already come to paſſe, there is yet one more of farre greater conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence readye to happen, yea euen ineuitable: for the ſaid D. of <hi>Parma</hi> hath through the ſaide iourney ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlipped the occaſion either to ſatiſfie the Princes of the Empire in their ſute to the King of Spaine for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of thoſe places that he holdeth and vſurpeth in the Dutches of Cleue &amp; Iulick, and other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> members of the Empire: either els, if he mean not to do it, which is very likely, to prouide himſelfe to defend &amp; kéep them perforce, which now he can hardly doo in time conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180884:10"/> in that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Princes of the Empire ſtanding diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content for that they were not ſatiſfied in their ſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds, are fully reſolued without further treatye or parly to bring down the mightieſt and ſtrongeſt army that hath béene leauyed in <hi>Germany</hi> in a long time, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the which neither the D. nor his maiſter haue any thing to oppoſe, ſo that of neceſſitie they will reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thoſe places, which hitherto haue beene the Mother nources of Flaunders: beſides that this iourney being enterpriſed vpon choller and diſdaine, it is to be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that ſuch an army being once in the field, wil not ſo ceaſe, neither ſhall want any pretences to proceede fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Theſe be the fruites of this his voiage, or rather we may ſaye, the effects of Gods iuſtice, who knoweth how to reuenge ſuch extreame preſumption and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when men doo leaſt look for it.</p>
            <p>This could not the king of Spaine wel comprehend in the ouerthrow of his great army which he had proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrongful inuaſion of England but muſt néeds heap on this new teſtimony, which beſides the loſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned doo alſo draw on the ouerthrow of the reputation of his only man, that was able to beare the name of a Captain, which heereafter he ſhall finde to be of as great importance vnto him, as any thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer he did. Theſe be euident tokens that Gods diuine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is purpoſed to fulfill his prophecies againſt this v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper and wrongfull enterpriſer as he did againſt <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> and <hi>Pharo,</hi> alſo that vpon his fal and ouerthrow he wil build vp the glory of thoſe whome this man purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to deſtroy. This therfore is all that can be gathered out of the trueth of the Duke of <hi>Parmas</hi> whole iourney after his entrye into Fraunce, vntil the laſt day of the moneth of Nouember, wherin he departed with ſhame which is not héere ſet downe to any other ende, but to ſerue as a remembrance to any ſuch his fauourers as liſt to vndertake the writing of this Hiſtory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:180884:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
